<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The churches sleepe expressed in a sermon preached at the court, in the celebration of the Kings Maiesties most ioyfull and happie entrance into this kingdome, the 24. of March last. By Anthonie Maxey, Batchelar in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Maiestie in ordinary.</title>
            <author>Maxey, Anthony, d. 1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100647</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836478</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836478</idno>
            <idno type="VID">755</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 755)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1318:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The churches sleepe expressed in a sermon preached at the court, in the celebration of the Kings Maiesties most ioyfull and happie entrance into this kingdome, the 24. of March last. By Anthonie Maxey, Batchelar in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Maiestie in ordinary.</title>
                  <author>Maxey, Anthony, d. 1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Este. for Clement Knight, dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the holy Lambe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D²  (-D2).</note>
                  <note>Usually bound with STC 17685: Maxey, Anthony. The goulden chaine of mans salvation (London, 1606).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:755:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:755:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Churches Sleepe, expreſsed in a Sermon Preached at the Court, in the Celebration of the Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt ioyfull and happie entrance into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the 24. of <hi>March</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Anthonie Maxey,</hi> Batchelar in Diuinitie, and Chaplaine to his Maieſtie in ordinary.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HEBREWES. 10.24.25.</bibl>
               <p>Let vs conſider one another, to prouoke vnto Loue and to good workes.</p>
               <p>Not forſaking the fellowſhip that we haue among our ſelues (as the manner of ſome is) but let vs exhort one an other.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>T. Eſte.</hi> for <hi>Clement Knight,</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the holy Lambe. 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:755:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:755:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cant. Chap. 2. Ver. 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>I charge you O yee daughters of Ieruſalem, by the Roes and Hindes of the field, that ye ſtir not vp, nor waken my Loue, vntill ſhe pleaſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the readier and more perfect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this verſe, it ſhall bee requiſite, very briefely, to ſet downe the <hi>order in placing this Booke,</hi> the <hi>Title,</hi> the <hi>Subiect matter,</hi> and ſo conſequently the <hi>Occaſion</hi> whereupon this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is inferred.</p>
            <p>Touching the placing and order of this Booke: in the firſt of <hi>Kings.</hi> 6. King <hi>Salomon</hi> in building the materiall Temple, hee framed three Courts: the outtermoſt, a great and large Court for the common people; next to that, an inner roome for the Prieſtes and Leuites, and laſt of all <hi>Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sanctorum,</hi> the holieſt of holies, onely for the high Prieſt to enter in. The ſame <hi>Salomon,</hi> in building vp the ſpirituall Temple of the Soule, he hath likewiſe framed three courts. Firſt the booke of the <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> as a great and outter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Court, wherein common people, and all ſorts of men, may learne, the ciuill and godly courſe of manners and diſcipline; next to that
<pb facs="tcp:755:3"/>
               <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> or the booke of the Preacher, as an inner court, leading vs on farther, and teaching vs to contemne the world; laſt of all, he brings vs into <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> to this <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Songs,</hi> wherein not euery one, but ſuch as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in diuine miſteries, and delight in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly contemplation, they may heere behold, the ſweet and miſticall coniunction betweene <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Church, betweene God and the ſoule.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Title.</hi> As there is <hi>Sabatum Sabati,</hi> and <hi>Sabatum Sabatorum,</hi> ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this is called the <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Songs.</hi> The <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Songs,</hi> for that it is ſoung to the King of Kings; The <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Songs,</hi> for that it contayneth the higheſt miſterie of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries: The <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Songs,</hi> becauſe of a thouſand &amp; fiue ſonets,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 4 32</note> which <hi>Salomon</hi> did endite, of them all this is moſt diuine moſt excellent. For it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth not any particular occaſion, as the ſongs of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Debora,</hi> but the publicke and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing eſtate of the Church, and therevpon for the excellencie, the ancient fathers cal it, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſure, the hidden <hi>Manna,</hi> and Paradiſe of the Soule.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Matter,</hi> our <hi>Subiect,</hi> the holy Ghoſt by ſweet and comfortable allegories, doth liuely and affectionately expreſſe, the holy and perfect loue between Chriſt and his bleſſed ſpouſe. So as <hi>Pliny</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:755:5"/>writeth,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cap. 25.</note> 
               <hi>that the Bees doe make outtermoſt part of their combs with the baſeſt hony, but doe incloſe the fineſt and pureſt hony within:</hi> So the outward duties of Religion, they are contained in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Precepts of the <hi>Prouerbs</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> but the diuine and heauenly miſteries, betwixt Chriſt and his Church, they lie hidden and are cloſely chouched in theſe Parables.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Occaſion</hi> where-vpon this Scripture is infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is this. The holy ſpouſe, the Church of God being in this world, as a Lilly amongſt Thornes,<note place="margin">2. &amp; 3. ver.</note> and as an Apple tree in the wilde forreſt, that is, oppreſſed with enimies, moleſted with Schiſme, Contention, and Hereſies, ſhe doth long to enioy the bleſſed preſence of Chriſt; at length vnder the peaceable and glorious raigne of King <hi>Salomon,</hi> comforted with his gratious ſpirit, ſhadowed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his protection, and ſatiſfied with his loue,<note place="margin">Honorius</note> with quiet reſt of heart and much content of minde, ſhee taketh her repoſe, and peaceably falles a ſleepe.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſtus digna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eſſe cuſtos ac vigill ſponſae,</hi> Chriſt vouchſafeth to become the Brides watchman or keeper. Allud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein to the manner of mariages in thoſe times, where at, were vſed to be ſung, two kinde of verſes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Scoliaſt. Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>criti. in Epitha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamium, Helen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> euening verſes to bring a ſleepe, and morning verſes to waken the Bride.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:755:6"/>But Chriſt in ardent affection,<note place="margin">Cap. ver. 2.3.8.7.5.4.</note> and tender care ouer his Church, in three ſeuerall places hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this great and ſolemne charge, that his Spouſe now being aſleepe, his Church being now in bleſſed reſt and proſeritie, no man waken her, no man cauſe any ſtir or trouble to bee raiſed.</p>
            <q>I charge you O yee daughters of Ieruſa. &amp;c.</q>
            <p>In theſe words, there is a <hi>Praecipe Chriſtianis,</hi> an high Commiſſion graunted out, for to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh and ſettle the good eſtate and peace of the Church. Wherein are to bee conſidered
<list>
                  <item>1. The Perſons.
<list>
                        <item>Firſt, who ſendeth— I, Laſtly, the date.</item>
                        <item>2 to whom — Daughters of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Laſtly, the date.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Charge.
<list>
                        <item>1. Manner — By the Roes and Hindes. Vntill ſhe pleaſe.</item>
                        <item>2. Subſtance—not to ſtir waken Chriſts loue. Vntill ſhe pleaſe.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Perſon who chargeth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, for the Perſon who it is that chargeth, and to whom this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is directed, it is requiſite to aske as the Spouſe doth in the fift Chapter and ninth verſe, <hi>Who is this beloued more
<pb facs="tcp:755:6"/>then another louer, that hee doth ſo charge.</hi> To di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and perſwade in matters of great weight and conſequence, there are theſe three required, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Wiſedome, Loue,<note place="margin">Ariſto. Rhet. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. Wiſedome to bee beleeued; Loue to be reſpected; Authoritie to be feared. Firſt, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for <hi>that is nimbler then all thinges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wiſ. 7.24.</note> and ſearcheth throughly, by reaſon of her pureneſſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Loue is requiſite,<note place="margin">Cant. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for <hi>it is ſtrong as death,</hi> there is nothing but a man will vndertake at the perſwaſion of a wiſeman, who doth intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue him.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Authority is required,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> for <hi>Etſi meliores ſunt quos ducit amor, tamen plures ſunt quos corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git timor;</hi> the better ſort are wonne by Loue, but the greater number are ouercome by Feare. Hee that giueth this charge it is our bleſſed Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſo ſaith the Spouſe in the next verſe, <hi>it is the voice of my well beloued:</hi> it is hee againſt whom for his Wiſedome to direct, for his Loue to comfort, for his Authoritie to puniſh, there is no exception to be taken, for <hi>Dominus locutus eſt, &amp; ego adiuro</hi> they are all one.</p>
               <p>And whereas hee begins with a charge, wee are to obſerue the Dialect and Acrimonie of the holy Ghoſt in chargeing.<note place="margin">Soto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maior.</note> For <hi>adiuratio eſt iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis quoddam genus,</hi> this adiuring and charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a kinde of ſwearing.<note place="margin">Gen. 24.3.</note> So that as <hi>Abraham</hi> cauſed his ſeruant to ſweare, and then charged
<pb facs="tcp:755:7"/>him not to take a wife for his Sonne of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo heere is an oath of Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call obedience required, that no man affiance himſelf, to any ſchiſmatical or hereticall Church, but onely the true Spouſe of Chriſt, ſhe muſt be, <hi>as the louing Hinde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and pleaſant Roe in thy ſight to delight in her loue continually.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The words of Gods ſpirit, they are not <hi>otioſa ſupplementa verborum,</hi> nor as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>words of the winde;</hi> but wher the holy Ghoſt fals on charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without queſtion there is ſome waightie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand;<note place="margin">Iob. 6.26.</note> and therefore in regard of the perſon who doth adiure &amp; charge, when the aſſemblie is broken vp, this charge muſt be thought vpon to be performed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Daughters of Ieruſalem.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE perſons to whome this charge is directed, is to the <hi>Daughters of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> that is, by the iudgement and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all interpreters, to the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> and to the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> eſpecially to the holy Prieſtes, who are attending vpon the Church, as waighting women on a <hi>Queene,</hi> or as louing daughters vpon their mothers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:755:7"/>They are named <hi>Daughters of Ieruſalem,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Daughters in their qualities reſemble their mother.<note place="margin">Ariſt. de ge. 4. cap. 3</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by <hi>Dauid</hi> it was made <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the mother citie in all <hi>Iudea,</hi> in the 12. of the Reuel: ſhee is ſaid to trauaile in birth, and in the 4. to the <hi>Galath.</hi> 26. it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the mother of vs all; a plaine periphraſis of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> as appeareth in the 18. of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> 28. it firſt tooke the name of <hi>Iebuſeus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Chana,</hi> and was called <hi>Iebus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſephus Arqueri.</note> after it was enlarged by <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> and called <hi>Salem,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Attonement,</hi> or the viſion of Peace; Hebr. 7. and 2. <hi>King of Salem; that is King of Peace.</hi> Thus then daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> are to bee vnderſtoode, Daughters that reſemble their mother, Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Peace. What? and is it to be feared, that <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſhall be diſturbed of her owne Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? they that profeſſe themſelues, to be children of the holy Citie, and ſhould continually pray for the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> are they ſuch ſtirrers that they muſt bee charged? I verely: the holy Ghoſt knew right well, both how &amp; to whom to ſpeake. For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Act. 20.30</note> euen from among your ſelues ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking peruerſe things, and ſeeking to draw Diſciples after them.</p>
               <p>When the Diuell ſaw, his Temples forſaken and his Oracles put to ſilence, hee deuiſed this as a ſpeciall ſupply to haue alwaies his agents in
<pb facs="tcp:755:8"/>or about the Church,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciuit. Dei. lib. 18. c. 51</note> 
                  <hi>Qui ſub vocabulo Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ano, doctrinae reſiſterent Chriſtianae,</hi> who vnder the title of a Chriſtian name, might euer be ready to reſiſt the Chriſtian doctrine. <hi>Inimici hominis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtici eius,</hi> our owne calling and countrymen, are our moſt vnkinde and cruell enimies. Had not diuers of vs, like vnnaturall children ſhaken off that reuerend obedience due to the Church our mother, but had ſhewed our ſelues (as heere we are named) <hi>Daughters of Ieruſalem,</hi> the holy ſpouſe of Chriſt, had neuer been ſo wounded at the heart, nor her patrimonie, ſo bouldly beene made a pray to ſacrilegious Atheiſts.</p>
               <p>Whereas we ſhould preach Chriſt Ieſus cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, that is, reconciliation by his bloud, holy life, repentance and good works, chriſtian Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſuch like, ſtill there is much a doe, about ſuch points, as make not to the furtherance of the people in good life and deuotion, but to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall, &amp; to the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the Church of God. It is a wofull of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, when the birth of the childe is the death of the mother. If <hi>It is</hi> run to his mother <hi>Progne,</hi> and bee betraied in her boſome: if when the childe aske bread, the father giue a Scorpion; if the Phiſition miniſter poiſon; if there bee no ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour in the iudge, <hi>Contra ſolitudinem &amp; inopiam,</hi> if one truth bee not generally taught of vs all, <hi>et locum vbi conſiſtat reperire non poteſt;</hi> if ſtill
<pb facs="tcp:755:8"/>there be a difference made betweene the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> and the <hi>Formaliſtes;</hi> and affirmed, that the <hi>Reformed</hi> though they loſe their liuings, yet they will keepe a good conſcience, but the <hi>Formaliſts</hi> will euer be of the ſame religion the king is of?</p>
               <p>If when we celebrate the Lords Supper, we play (as they ſay) a pageant of our owne, and make poore ſilly ſoules beleeue, they haue an Engliſh maſſe; if Church men affirme, that our Church hath in it ſtill, ſo many black marks, that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall children of the Church cannot diſcerne it? what hope can be conceiued, that the bleſſed Spouſe ſhall euer attaine, vnto any ſetled and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſt? The people in all ages, they haue euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to heare of the faultes and frailties both of their gouernours &amp; of their teachers; it hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene laughing cheere to the ignorant multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to ſee ſtrange innouations, change in the courſe of religion, and men of the Church, at variance and contention, yet all this is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to aduiſe, but ſtill, euen vpon no occaſion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers are euer troubling the ſtate, and murmuring againſt the gouernment eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt, he directeth this charge, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially vnto vs, &amp; calleth vs <hi>Daughters of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
                  <hi>piè blanditur, ac ſuauitèr allicìt, Daughters</hi> for loue, <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> for peace; teaching vs thereby, humilitie, obedience to the chriſtian Maieſtrate, peace, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and ſubmiſſion to the Church our mother?
<pb facs="tcp:755:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo that, if wee doe ioy in the proſperitie of our country, if we doe long after the floriſhing eſtate of the Church (aboue all others) we muſt be knit together in vnitie and peace.<note place="margin">Gel. 5.15.</note> 
                  <hi>For if we bite one an other, wee ſhall be conſumed one of another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely, the Lord is with King <hi>Salomon,</hi> God is with our King, hee hath giuen him wiſedome, riches, and honour, hee hath built him a glorious pallace,<note place="margin">Cant. 3.9.</note> the timber is of Lebanon, the pillers of ſiluer, the ornaments of gold, the worke doth proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in his hands, and there remaines nothing but that <hi>it may bee paued throughout, with the loue of the Daughters of Ieruſalem.</hi> Therefore you that bee Magiſtrates, Parlament men, flowers of the land, and ornaments of your Countrie, heere alſo called <hi>Daughters of Ieruſalem,</hi> doe you by all good meanes procure the Peace of the Church. Giue no encouragement to humorous men; doe not fauour their diſorderly proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; win them by your authoritie, perſwade them in your loue, to peace and conformitie. It is ſaid of Saint <hi>Ciprian,</hi> that with teares he bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thoſe, who in the time of perſecution denied Chriſt; much more is their contempt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſenes to be lamented, who in the time of the Churches proſperitie doe wilfully forſake Chriſt: for what is it elſe to forſake Chriſt, but without iuſt cauſe, with out any ſure ground, to forſake
<pb facs="tcp:755:3"/>that bleſſed calling, wherof before God and men, before Saints and Angels, they haue made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profeſſion before the Church.</p>
               <p>Is this integritie? is this humbleneſſe of mind, and an heart truely knit and deuoted vnto God? No verily. <hi>Is in amore Dei maior erit, qui pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos ad eius amorem trahit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. in hom.</note> That man ſhall bee accepted moſt in Gods loue, who doth win moſt to the holy loue of God. It is a bleſſed thing, to be euen a doore keeper in the houſe of God: and it ſauours of an humble minde, of a ſweet ſpirit, to become all things to all men, by all poſſible meanes to win ſome. Thus did Chriſt teach in his life, and thus did he performe in his death. <hi>Perdidit vitam potiùs quam perdidit obedientiam.</hi> But, if it be ſo, that nothing can preuaile with theſe men, and that they will needes leaue of to be <hi>Daughters of Ieruſalem:</hi> then here is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a charge giuen to fore-warne them by word, but in the 15. ver. there followes an attachment. If <hi>I charge</hi> will not ſerue, the <hi>take vs the foxes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 2.15</note> 
                  <hi>that deſtroy the vines,</hi> muſt follow: <hi>If Arons</hi> rod cannot ſway, <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt ſtinge: <hi>Fitches are to be beaten with a ſtaffe, and cummin with arod.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer will not doe,<note place="margin">Eza. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> the Law of thy God and the Kings law, let him haue iudgement without delay. S. <hi>Baſile</hi> ſaith, that Magiſtrate is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with out bowels and compaſſion, who ſuffereth diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the church vnpuniſhed. Diuers queſtions,
<pb facs="tcp:755:4"/>beginning onely to ariſe, betweene the Diſciples of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and our Sauiour, holy writers haue this obſeruation, that God in his wiſedome, did ſuffer the death of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to haſten,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3 25.</note> that there might be no ſects nor diuiſion in the Church.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. Theodo.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Very loth haue I euer beene, to be ſeene at any time to meddle in theſe troubles of the Church, and therefore (the Lord knoweth my heart) I ſpeake not in bitterneſſe to exaſperate any mans thoughts againſt them. But in this caſe, who is offended, and I burne not? by lamentable experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doe I know, what ſtrange and wofull effects, theſe diſordered courſes haue brought forth. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, in whoſe vertuous and louely ſocietie, my heart hath often ioyed, and ſome, for whom na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would cauſe a man to cry out, (would to god I had dyed for thee my brother;) ſome of theſe haue forſaken both friends and country, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (men of excellent parts in humaine lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whereas they had purpoſed to take holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, by reaſon of theſe contentions, they fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and embraced this preſent world. Therefore in thoſe things, which concern the glory of God, the peace and proſperitie of the Church:<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
                  <hi>Optima legum inſtitutio, vt non ſolùm ſint, ſed vt latis pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reatur.</hi> As it is a bleſſed thing to haue begun well, ſo it is the crowne of glory to perſeuere in well doing, to perſiſt by all good meanes, that as much as poſſible may bee, from the Orcades to the
<pb facs="tcp:755:4"/>South ſeas, from the Iriſh pale to the Weſterne bounds, there may bee one publike, perfect, and Chriſtian Peace amongſt vs: for feare leaſt as by the diſcord of the <hi>Arians</hi> innumerable people fell away,<note place="margin">Dluus. Hilar. lib. contra Conſt. Auguſt.</note> from Chriſtianitie to Gentiliſme and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, ſo by reaſon of our diſcord, they neuer ceaſe, to fall away as faſt to Atheiſine &amp; impietie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Roes and Hindes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the Perſons you haue heard, novv commeth in the charge it ſelfe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in firſt we are to conſider the <hi>Manner,</hi> which is very ſweet and proper. For being in the fieldes and alluding to ſhepheards according to the tenor of the <hi>Canticle,</hi> hee doth charge by the <hi>Roes</hi> and <hi>Hindes</hi> of the field. Why wee ſhould bee charged by <hi>Roes</hi> and <hi>Hindes,</hi> (ſuch a ſtrange kinde of adiuration) and what is ment by them, there is great varietie of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, amongſt all writers. In the originall tongue, <hi>Tzeboath</hi> and <hi>Ailoth,</hi> the Hebrew words they doe ſignifie <hi>exercitus &amp; virtutes,</hi> wherevnto the <hi>Septuagints</hi> agreeing, doe tranſlate it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. O yee Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:755:5"/>I charge you, by the royall armies, and ſtrength of the field.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aponius</hi> in his 4. booke,<note place="margin">Aponius.</note> ſaith, we are adiured by <hi>Roes and Hindes.</hi> For example ſake, <hi>quòd horu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt amor ardentiſsimus,</hi> becauſe of all other beaſts, their loue, in feeding, and keeping quietly one with an other, is moſt peaceable and affectionate: <hi>Per Hinnulos &amp; Capreas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rupertus.</note> that is, ſaith <hi>Rupertus,</hi> by the holy Patriarks; <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> who in their generations were men of peace: <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> hee expoundeth it,<note place="margin">Tho. Aqui Lyra.</note> by the holy Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, <hi>Lyra</hi> ſaith we are charged by <hi>Roes and Hindes</hi> for that theſe beaſts are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to poyſon, and fellow helpers againſt ſuch as hurt them.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard ſerm. 53. Beza.</note> hee adiureth by the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who are as ſwift as <hi>Roes and Hindes, Beza,</hi> (whoſe expoſition is very good) he ſaith; the ſpirit of God, doth call the very dum creatures to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes againſt ſtirrers in the Church. Some expound <hi>Roes and Hindes</hi> to bee the chiefe theologicall vertues, adiuring vs by our faith, hope, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Others they ſay wee are adiured <hi>amore quo tenemini Sanctis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hugo. Cand.</note> by that loue and reuerend du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which we doe owe to the Saints and reuerend Fathers of the Church. To bee ſhort: <hi>Gregory, Gorrhan, Caſsiodore, Ambroſe, Origen, Honorius, Anſelmus, Angelomus,</hi> almoſt euery author doth differ in his expoſition. So that as the Poet cryed
<pb facs="tcp:755:9"/>out, <hi>Quid clamem? quae fata vocem? quae numina poſcam?</hi> ſo all authors are at a ſtande, and cannot tell, either in heauen or in earth, or amongſt the creatures, what to call to witneſſe, that they might ſufficiently charge. But that they might be ſure to make all men fearefull to ſtirre or trouble the Churches peace, euery one doth adiure by that which in his ſenerall iudgement is moſt forcible. Amongſt the reſt,<note place="margin">Venerab. Beda.</note> the expoſition of <hi>Venerable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> is very ſignificant and religious. I charge you by the <hi>Roes and Hindes,</hi> that is ſaith he, <hi>per deliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as agri,</hi> by the ſoules and tender conſciences of the ignorant and ſimple people, they are the <hi>Roes and Hindes</hi> which we muſt hunt after, and ſtudy to take. And very fitly are they compared to <hi>Roes and Hindes,</hi> becauſe as, <hi>Pliny,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P li. lib 8. cap 53. Solinus. lib 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> and <hi>Solinus</hi> writeth, they are moſt tender and fearefull of all beaſts, affrited with any noiſe, checked with the leaſt foile, tourned out of courſe with the cracking of a ſticke, preſently make head another way, and when they are once out of their wonted walke, <hi>Erranti in via, nullus eſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus,</hi> they run they know not whither, euen to their owne death: Such is the nature and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of common people, ſoone ſtird vp, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led awry, ſometimes running full head one way, on a ſodaine turned as much an other.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.24. Act. 12.2.</note> Therefore it is a ſeruile courſe, and bewraies a vaine and proud ſpirit for any, eſpecially men of religion
<pb facs="tcp:755:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and vnderſtanding, to fit the fancies, and ſeeke to win vnto themſelues the applauſe of common people.<note place="margin">Plato de Rep.</note> 
                  <hi>Plato</hi> in his common wealth forbids men, to tange vp and downe, to ring away other mens <hi>Bees,</hi> yet the onely glory of ſome men is, to get, flockers, and followers after them, by tanging and iangling in matters of no importance. Surely, as a weake and feeble braine, followeth the waxing and waining of the Moone, ſo the braine-ſicke humour of the multitude is ſubiect and pliable to euery change and reuolution. Whereupon <hi>Homer</hi> compares the diſpoſition of common people to <hi>the ſtanding corne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Homer.</note> ther comes a puffe, and blowes it all on the one ſide, there comes an other blaſt, and ſwayes it as much on the other ſide. It is a fit compariſon made by the Kingly Prophet.<note place="margin">Pſa. 65.7.</note> 
                  <hi>It is the Lord that ſtilleth the rage of the Sea, the noiſe of the Waues, and the madneſſe of the people;</hi> iumping therein with the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> 17. Chapter, where the nature of the people is compared vnto the billowes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of the trouble ſome and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sea. So eaſily ſet a gog, ſo delighted with nouelties, ſo full of alteration and change are the affections of common people.</p>
               <p>In the 28. of the <hi>Acts.</hi> Saint <hi>Paule</hi> whileſt the Viper hung vpon his hand, he was a <hi>murderer,</hi> againe, the Viper ſhaken off, in the turning of an hand, he <hi>was a God.</hi> In the 3. of <hi>Ezra</hi> and the 12.
<pb facs="tcp:755:10"/>the <hi>people wept</hi> becauſe they had no Temple: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when the Temple was builded, then <hi>they wept</hi> as faſt againe, becauſe the glory of the ſecond was not like the firſt. In the time of queene <hi>Mary,</hi> there was lamentation, and crying out, that I do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry was ſet vp, the Church polluted, and the Goſpell taken away: afterward when through the great mercie of God, the Goſpell was aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and the light thereof did comfortably ſhine throughout the whole kingdome, then they mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mured and cryed out as faſt againe, that wee had <hi>no Church, no Miniſtry, truth was wrapt vp in Ceremonies, and all was Antichriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 19. of the <hi>Acts, Demetrius</hi> and other ſubtill heads of the tradſe men of Epheſus, (meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their owne gaine) raiſed a great tumult, and getting the people together, cryed out, <hi>great is Diana of the Epheſians;</hi> preſently the people were carried with ſuch a tempeſt of fury, that the cittie was all in an vprore, they can and ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whether they liſt in great confuſion, much violence was offered, and yet at laſt as appearerh in the 32. verſe, the moſt part <hi>knew not wherefore they were come tog ther.</hi> In like ſort,<note place="margin">Nobiles qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am praeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>merum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge unt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ann, 1583.</note> not many yeeres agone, diuers perſonages of great credit and countenance (they and their predeceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urs being long ſince enriched, by the reuenues of the Church and fearing to loſe them) apprehending preſently the ſucceſſe, inuegled many weake
<pb facs="tcp:755:11"/>men, young diuines, tradeſ-men, artificers, and ſuch like, and they all cryed out, for <hi>the Geneua diſcipline,</hi> and Scottiſh reformation in the Churh. The ignorant multitude once ſtirred vp, the whole land was in ſects and tumults, the ſtate was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, the Prince was diſobeyed, good lawes were neglected, by Libels, Pamphlets, by conſeale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by treacheries, by ſundry foule diſorders, violence and diſgrace was offered,<note n="b" place="margin">A booke of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline compiled after the Geneua faſhion by M. Knox, &amp; others, reiected of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and termed a deuout i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Another booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ph eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae ſacra verbo Dei diſcripta, correct d altered &amp; amended about. 1587.</note> to many ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and worthy callings in this land, and yet I dare ſay, the moſt part neuer knew what they did deſire. Nay, I dare confidently affirme, that the chiefeſt &amp; learnedſt ſectaries of thoſe times, and euen at this day, not ſixe of them, did euer fully and ſoundly agree, in the maine points, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of erecting, this their Goddeſſe <hi>Diana,</hi> this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected diſcipline and reformation. Yet behold and obſerue the effects.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſilly <hi>Roes and Hindes</hi> once ſtirred vp, they flockt together and aſſembled in woods; they haunted priuate conuenticles in the night; they had ſecret Printers in euery corner, the publike congregation grew odious, the holy word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments were deſpiſed: at length they affirmed plainely there was no true Miniſter in the Church of England, and ſo ſome fled beeyond Seas, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gaue vp their calling, lurking idly in other mens ho ſes, ſeducing their mindes, and waſting their eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. While theſe reformers thus ranne
<pb facs="tcp:755:11"/>their courſe, honeſt plaine men, ſimple people, beholding ſuch parts taking and contention, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch acceptions of perſons, and varietie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, they in their ignorance ſtood at a gaze: ſome fell away to the Church of Rome, others waxed neither hot not cold, Athiſme crept in, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion was laid aſide, God exceedingly diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the eſtate both of Church and common wealth very much defaced, I ſay no more of theſe <hi>Roes and Hindes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>If then we regard the ſaluation, of ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by rooting out all Athiſme and Superſtition, if wee tender their peaceable and Chriſtian life, who are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, miſſe-led vpon euery light occaſion, then we muſt wholy lay aſide, all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and difference whatſoeuer: with one hart, with one conſent, we muſt all preach one and the ſelfe ſame doctrine, all vſe the ſame ceremonies, thereby to win the people to Godlines of life, and holy reuerence; and alwaies (in regard of their weaknes) we muſt be ſhie and fearefull of ſtirring in the Church. The very Heathen haue taught vs diſcreation in this point.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the wiſe <hi>Grecians</hi> the difficult points of their religion,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciui. Del. li. 4. cap. 38</note> were neuer laid open to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing of the ignorant people, but cloſed vp with ſilence. <hi>Varro</hi> that notable, and learned writer, remoued thoſe bookes which he wrote, touching
<pb facs="tcp:755:12"/>the deepeſt queſtions &amp; miſteries in Theologie, from the ſight and knowledge of the multitude, <hi>Scholis verò ac parietibus clauſit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de ciui. Dei. li. 6. cap. 5.</note> he reſerued them priuate to the learned Schooles.</p>
               <p>Aboue all others, the holy Apoſtles and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant Fathers of bleſſed memory, were ſo chary in this point, hat if any doubt aroſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or controuerſie fell out among them: they did not by and by ſet forth bitter inuectiues and ſedicious Phamphlets, they did not put vp cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous bils to temporall courts, they did not creepe and couch to lay men, for the boulſtring and bearing out of any diſorders in the Church, they did not haunt &amp; trouble Chriſtian Princes, with bould and vnaduiſed petitions, but as wee may ſee,<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> by the Apoſtles <hi>Acts.</hi> 15. A matter of great conſequence, was orderly and louingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſſed at <hi>Ieruſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> (the Schoole of the Prophets) and ſo peaceably ended by the chiefe and moſt excellent Apoſtles. This preſident and worthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, was truely followed by Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Ruffmus,</hi> by Saint <hi>Auguſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> by <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Epiphamus,</hi> by the good <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in the time of <hi>Arrius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Niceph. eccle hiſt. lib. 8 50. Paulus Diaco.</note> by <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> who ſent priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Paule</hi> Patriarch of Conſtantinople: thus they conferred peaceably together, they wrote priuately one the each other, and ſo (neuer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the people acquainted) doubts being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and controuerſies ended euery man did reſt
<pb facs="tcp:755:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſatisfied in his obedience and went peaceably on in his ſeuerall calling. Theſe holy and graue men conſidered well, that the ſoules of the ignorant people were precious, their mindes like <hi>Roes and Hindes,</hi> eaſily miſſecaried, ſoone ſtirred vp, and quickly driuen from their wonted layer, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the good ſhepherd in the 23. Pſalme, they <hi>fed them peaceably in greene paſtures,</hi> they led them not vnto torrentes, to troubleſome whirlepooles, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the waters of reſt,<note place="margin">Heresbaci in Pſal. 23.</note> and as the originall doth infer to the ſweete ſtreames that <hi>run quietly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Stir not.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſubſtance of this charge, is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Firſt, not to ſtir in reſpect of the danger: Secondly, not to waken, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Spouſe, who is fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, and peaceably taking reſt. It is dangerous to ſtir, for that a rent or ſchiſme in the Church, is like a wound in the Soule, or a great breach in the Sea, there is almoſt nothing able to cloſe it vp againe. Howſoeuer at the firſt it ſeemes of ſmall reckning, and of no importance, yet, it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhewes it ſelfe at the beeginning in the right colors, but <hi>creſcit eundo,</hi> it creeps on and gathers ſtrength, and we ſhall neuer read, that the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
<pb facs="tcp:755:13"/>point of any Schiſme, did euer reſt, or ſtay it ſelfe, vntill it came to a full periode, of a plaine hereſie.<note place="margin">Hieron. Eccli. 11 32. Niceph. eccle. hiſt. li. 8. cap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Nullum ſchiſma, non ſibi aliquam poſted confingit haereſim. Of one little ſparke is made a great fire. Arrian</hi> his hereſie, it was but a ſparke (as <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephorus</hi> doth write) firſt raiſed by one <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Bancalis,</hi> becauſe an other was preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, yet this ſparke ſet all Aſia, Africke, and Europe on fire, &amp; ſo poyſoned the ſpawne of the Church,<note place="margin">Caſsiod. li. 1. cap. 12</note> in the floriſhing ſpring of worthie <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> that euen to this day, it neuer recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the loſſe againe. <hi>Mahomet</hi> that Antichriſtian infidell, firſt, began his ſect with a few followers, and becauſe <hi>Heraclius</hi> the Emperour let him run on,<note place="margin">Carion. anno. Do. 641.</note> neglecting him as not worthy to be defeated, ſhortly after vnder colour of his religion, hee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ran Aſia, defaced the Eaſt Church, ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the glorious Empire of Conſtantinople, and ſo continues to this day the ſcourge of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bleidan. Bellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticanum abſumpſit Germano. rum. 150000. vei eſt in vita Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis Rom. Pontificis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>Did not the <hi>Anabaptiſtes</hi> of late yeares. 1525. euen of a ſmall ſparke, raiſe ſuch a flame in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, that growing at length to parts taking, by the baſe multitude, Temples, and cities were ſet on fire, baniſhment and proſcription inflicted vpon the innocent, and at length a butchery maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaker made of fiftie thouſand people ſlaine at one time, and an hundred thouſand Chriſtians mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at an other. They began with the Biſhops,
<pb facs="tcp:755:13"/>and Clergie,<note place="margin">Bullinger.</note> but they ended with the depoſing of ciuill Magiſtrates and deſtruction of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>The ground and primatiue cauſe of all the contentions raiſed heretofore in our Church, was at the firſt a ſmall diſcontentment, a matter of priuate grudge, a little ſparke: but by a bould admonition giuen at that time to the high court of Parliament, it wakened all England,<note place="margin">Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and ſet a number of tongues and pens on fire, (not with ſuch fire as fell on the Alter, and ſanctified the Sacrifice) but with the fire of bitternes, ſchiſme, &amp; contention, which could neuer yet be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quenched to this day.</p>
               <p>From this ſparke, as from Hydra, what a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of poyſoned heades ſprong vp: Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Browniſts, Puritaines, Cathariſts, Atheiſts, the famille of loue, and ſuch like. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thoſe worthy and learned men, who fled in queene <hi>Maries</hi> time (as <hi>Iohn Bale, Richard Cox, Iohn Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>khurſt, William Burloe, Alexander Nowell; Iohn Iewell; Edwin Sands, Edmond Grindall,</hi> and very many more) maintained the gouernement of the Church of England, vſed in their holy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, the forme of ſeruice, and order of cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which were eſtabliſhed in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, &amp; ratified againe by good queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> yet behold, contrary to the iudgement &amp; courſe of theſe learned and holy men, what ſtrange,
<pb facs="tcp:755:14"/>what fiery and ſtirring concluſions were raiſed. That the choiſe of Miniſters ſhould ſtand vpon the approbation of the people,<note n="a" place="margin">Cart. wright. Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli. to the Parlia. 56.</note> and that they are all of equall authoritie: that the Church gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was vtterly vnlawfull and Antichriſtian: That the Article of our faith, touching Chriſts deſcention into hell was foiſted into the Creede: That<note n="b" place="margin">Hacket executed. Feſtidies. ſunt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modè a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolendi.</note> the Lords prayer, by our Sauiour himſelfe commaunded, was not to be vſed: That<note n="c" place="margin">Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiks in Berry.</note> no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liday might be obſerued, but onely the Saboth: That no<note n="d" place="margin">Defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded openly in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie.</note> father or humaine writer might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged in the Pulpet: That the Booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, was to bee aboliſhed: That all the Ceremonies of our Church were Popiſh, and to be ſwept away:<note n="e" place="margin">Mart iu. r. Adm. pa. 25.</note> That the callings of Biſhops, was an Antichriſtian &amp; diuelliſh hierarchy: That reformation of Religion, belongeth to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaltie:<note n="g" place="margin">Buccha de iure regni. Page. 61.</note> &amp; that the people are better then the King, and of greater authoritie: That<note n="h" place="margin">Scottiſh presbetary in priſon at this day.</note> the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitery and not the Prince was to bee ſupreme gouernours in matters Eccleſiaſticall.</p>
               <p>This ſparke, what a number of<note n="i" place="margin">Martin iunior. Martin ſenior. Martin prote. Martinus Epiſt. His Epitome. Hay any work.</note> ſeditious books, biting Libels, and ſlanderous Pamphlets, did it raiſe? This ſparke amongſt our ſelues, what heart burning, what boyling and ſecret grudges (by the neglect of ſome, and applauding of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,) did it breede? This ſparke amongſt great
<pb facs="tcp:755:14"/>perſonages, what palpable hypocriſie,<note place="margin">Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks, ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nembred.</note> what ſoule ſacriledge did it cauſe to bee committed? This ſparke, what a gap did it open, and what way did it make into the hearts of many men, firſt, to doubt of the truth, and ſo after to bee won to the Church of Rome? amongſt the Roes and Hinds; what diſordered conuenticles,<note place="margin">In Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ſoſwich. Couentre Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bridge</note> what prophane actions, what ſecret whiſperings, what vile trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries did this ſparke procure, Townes, Cities, Vniuerſities, the whole Land was on flame with this ſparke.</p>
               <p>In the peaceable eſtate of any Church, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue any old point of hereſie, to ſet on ſoote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new opinion, any ſchiſme, or intricate queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it proues like the cloud that <hi>Elias</hi> ſaw,<note place="margin">1. Kin 18.44.</note> at the firſt his ſeruant looked, and hee ſaw nothing; by and by hee bad him looke againe, and it bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ariſe as big as a mans fiſt, at length it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the whole skie with darkeneſſe, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately there followed a ſtorme. In like ſort the moſt dangerous hereſies that euer were, at the firſt they haue beene raiſed of a ſmall matter, and ſeemed nothing, but in the ende they haue ſhadowed the face of the Church, and cauſed immeſurable bloudſhed. Nay, it is to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, in the courſe of all ages and times, that the greateſt Monarchies, and moſt floriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world, haue neuer receiued ſuch fearefull blowes, and vnexpected downe-fals by
<pb facs="tcp:755:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>open and forraine enemies, as they haue done by ſtealing innouations and ſecrettreaſons, firſt, raiſed by ſects and hereſies, in religion. There is nothing doth ſo knit together the hearts of men, as the band of Faith: againe, there is nothing doth cauſe ſuch deadly hatred, and mortall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilitie, as difference and diſcord in religion. In a word, Diſſention is the ordinarie gate, whereat deſtruction entreth in. The deſtruction of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, it firſt began with the ciuill diſcord of <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Eleazer:</hi> By the diſſention of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the <hi>Eaſt Church,</hi> the Turke firſt entred into Hungary: and ſo generally diſcord hath euer wrought the tranſlating of Kingdomes, &amp; finall deſolation. Therefore beloued Fathers, and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren all, I humbly beſeech you in the name of the liuing God, <hi>Submit your ſelues, to all manner ordinance of man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Peter, 2.13. Tit. 3.1. 1. Tim. 2.1 Rom. 13.1.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Lords ſake:</hi> euery man ſtand faſt in loialtie and faithfull obedience, goe peaceably on in that calling, wherein God hath placed you, ceaſe to be contentious, and with an humble ſpirit, ſtriue to walke before the Lord in truth, and with a perfect heart. That ſo, the God of conſolation, and peace, who hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt vs the Goſpell of peace, and hath ſet ouer vs a religious King, a louer of peace, and hath ſetled in his dominions a ioyfull peace, may giue vnto his Spouſe &amp; graunt vnto his Church, loue, vnitie and a perpetuall peace, for his owne
<pb facs="tcp:755:15"/>name and glory ſake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Waken not.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond part of this charge, is not <hi>to waken</hi> Chriſts ſpouſe,<note place="margin">Cant. 8.9.</note> for ielouſie is cruell as the graue, and if any man be ſo hardy and bould as to waken his <hi>Loue,</hi> it ſhall ſurely bee reuenged. In the 54. of <hi>Eſay.</hi> and the 5. as Chriſt is there called the <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> he that made thee is thy <hi>Husband,</hi> euen the Lord of Hoſtes: ſo <hi>Reuel.</hi> 29. &amp; 9. the Church is called the pride or the Lambs wife, and here very gratiouſly hee vouchſafeth to call her his <hi>Loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is much a doe, many greuances or louers bee vnited. The Church of the Iewes, was 480. yeares vnder perſecution of <hi>Pharao,</hi> and vexed by the Gentiles, or euer it came to enioy peace and proſperitie vnder <hi>Salomon.</hi> The primatiue Church was 300. yeares militant vnder ten grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous perſecutions or euer it came to be dormant vnder <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great. This church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land in times paſt, hath ſeemed to bee forſaken of her louer, and oftentimes ſince ſundry broiles, many diſcontentments haue fallen out, or euer ſhee might hope aſſuredly, tò enioy any quiet reſt indeed. <hi>She went about and ſought him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant 3.2.</note> 
                  <hi>whom
<pb facs="tcp:755:16"/>her ſoule loued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 15</note> 
                  <hi>and found him not. But now as a bridegrome reioyceth ouer the Bride, ſo hath God reioyced ouer this Land, and deckea his Loue with ornaments, in a moſt excellent manner, ſhee is bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come glorious and of perfect beautie, her name is ſpred through the world, and other nations doe taſt and are ſatisfied with the breaſts of her conſolation.</hi> If wee aduiſedly conſider, and call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, the bloudy maſſakers of <hi>France,</hi> and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Religion ſtill therein: the weariſome broiles of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and vnſetled eſtate of the Church amongſt them:<note place="margin">The kings Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ted at Rutheuer. 1, 84.</note> If wee ſet beefore our eyes, the high indignities offered heretofore in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to our moſt worthy and religious King <hi>Iames;</hi> the ſodaine and ſundry mutines, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores euer and anon ariſing from their presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall diſcipline:<note place="margin">The kings Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciped at Strine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to take the Caſtle. &amp; in the end to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſo his ſaſeue.</note> the vnſtayed and diſcontented cariage, the poore and deſpiſed eſtate of ſuch Church-men, as firſt hoped, but now cannot, with any reuerend gouernment rule therein, then muſt wee needes confeſſe, happy are wee in our ſetled peace, and moſt bleſſed in the Godly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie which we enioy.</p>
               <p>This proſperitie, this reſt of the Church, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Salomon</hi> then, and ſuch like noble, wiſe, and religious Kings at this day, is compared vnto <hi>Sleepe,</hi> and out of this ſleep, the Church may not bee wakened. For throughout this whole Song, Chriſt is neuer ſaid to haue ſlept with his Spouſe,
<pb facs="tcp:755:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>neither is there at any time mention of ſleepe, but preſently (as in three ſeuerall places) follows, this charge; that no man waken.</p>
               <p>There is one kinde of ſleepe,<note place="margin">Ouid. Homer.</note> which is <hi>Mortis imago. Homer</hi> cals it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, deaths bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or a dead ſleepe. Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the 6. to the Epheſ. 18. hee termes the death of ſinne, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſpirit of ſlumber: the Church of Sardis in the 3. of the Reuel. is ſaid to be in this ſlumber. Our Church alſo was ſuppoſed to haue beene in this ſleepe, and thereupon, thoſe <hi>Good men, Vaux, Peircy, and Catesbie, reſolued to take puniſhment of the wickedneſſe of theſe times and to waken vs.</hi> But howſoeuer the <hi>Spouſe might ſleep,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">O feareful wakning. Cant. 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>her heart was waking,</hi> the prayers of the Saints continually crying, kept the mercie of the Lord <hi>waking</hi> ſo that though wee ſleepe, the keeper of Iſraell did neither ſlumber nor ſleepe, Hee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the eyes, and wakned the heart of his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ſeruant, to doubt of the danger, diſcry the plot, and to preuent the <hi>Deadly Blow.</hi> He is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, the Lord is magnified, they are fallen, wee ſtand vpright, and bleſſed bee the God of our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>There is another kinde of <hi>Sleepe,</hi> which is <hi>Ros naturae,</hi> the ſweat or the dew of nature, of this ſleepe the Phiſitions ſay, it is the repaſt of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the greateſt comfort in nature that may bee. Such a <hi>ſleepe,</hi> is this of the Spouſe, <hi>ex rore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uino,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:755:17"/>the dewe of heauen hath fallen vpon her, he hath giuen his beloued <hi>ſleepe, et ſucro ſilentia ſommo procurat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bemard.</note>
               </p>
               <p>God forbid I ſhould come hither in the name of my God, and ſtand here before this holy and honorable preſence, to wound my conſcience, by deliuering an vntruth, or by blanching of ſin and corruption, to diſhonour my holy calling. No, <hi>viuit Iehouath,</hi> The Lord knoweth my thoughts, I ſpeake the truth, (as I conceiue) from my ſoule, to the glorious praiſe of our euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and to the great comfort and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of all that heare me. As it is in the former part of this Chapter. <hi>Chriſt hath now brought his Spouſe into the wine ſeller,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſes. 4.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>he hath ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her with flagons, &amp; comforted her with aples, his left hand is vnder her head, and his right hand doth imbrace her,</hi> that is, ſatisfied in great meaſure both with temporall and ſpirituall bleſſings, ſhee doth reſt in great proſperitie. <hi>Shee hath laid her downe in peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.9.</note> 
                  <hi>and taketh her reſt, for now the Lord hath made her to dwell in ſafetie.</hi> O let vs praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and neuer be aſhamed, to declare the wonders, and to publiſh the bleſſings, which hee hath brought vpon vs this day. Our eyes doe ſee them, our thoughts muſt needes acknowledge them, and our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (wee finde by late experience) with ſecret
<pb facs="tcp:755:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>and great mallice doe enuie them. Giue me leaue therefore (I humbly beſeech you) euen for the glory of Gods bleſſed name (whoſe exceeding mercie we are bound to acknowledge) &amp; alſo for a teſtimonie of our owne priuate duties, to make ſome relation of thoſe benefites, which wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy by the bleſſed gouernment of our gratious Soueraigne, whoſe happy and ioyfull entrance into this Kingdome, wee doe celebrate this day.</p>
               <p>It is a plaine, but an excellent principle.<note place="margin">Euripides.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Let him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer take vpon him, nor deſire to rule, who hath not firſt learned to obey, and to forbeare. It is well knowne vnto vs all, ſundry times hath the quiet ſtate of this Realme beene diſturbed, much hurly burly raiſed, many treaſons brued, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and procuring the death of our former <hi>Queene,</hi> pretending moſt what, ſome title and intereſt vnto the crowne, but beehold, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the apparant truth of his Maieſties ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle was openly knowen to all the States in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and that long before, he might haue procured ſtronge meanes, to haue inueſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;<note place="margin">Forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancce.</note> with the honour and poſſeſſion of the ſame: yet ſtill, did he patiently abide the Lords leaſure, as one who truely feared God, hee neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined with France, nor complotted with Spaine; he neuer ſtirred vp, either ſubiect within, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine power without, but that which is yet very
<pb facs="tcp:755:18"/>ioyfull to remember, and ſeldome performed of naturall brothers in one familie, two mightie Princes, <hi>good Queene Elizabeth, and our bleſſed King,</hi> moſt amiably they did liue, and loue, (and as it were in one land) peaceably raigne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>When God had ended her daies in peace, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many diſtracted feares, wherewith the hearts of all beegan ſodainely to bee perplexed; how bleſſed were we in the preſent ſucceſſion of the crowne,<note place="margin">Succeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> the happie gouernement whereof, did calmely come in, and peaceably ariſe, as after a ſhort night, the cheerefull and faire morning Sun-ſhine.</p>
               <p>How ſecure is now the ſtate, in the vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed apparance of bleſſed <hi>Iſſue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſſue.</note> a ſtay to the Land, and comfort to euery good ſubiects heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed art thou,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pron. 28.15</note> 
                  <hi>O Land</hi> (ſaith the Scripture) <hi>whoſe Prince is the Sonne of Nobles.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Royall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</note> In the royall diſcent of this imperiall crowne, the Roſe is not onely ſprounge from the Red and White, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from the noble off-ſpring of both houſes, <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Yorke</hi> (thereby moſt happely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away all occaſion of ciuill diſſention) but moreouer happy are wee in our ſelues, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to other nations, in the quiet and lawfull vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Kingdomes. Phantaſticall humors did pleaſe themſelues a while, and ſelfe conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heades, haue vainely diſcourſed with idle
<pb facs="tcp:755:18"/>ſimilies, againſt the ordinance of God in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe: but (leauing the future ſucceſſe, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther coniunction to prayer, forbearance, and time) in this one bleſſing,<note place="margin">Vnion.</note> we may plainely bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the extraordinarie mercies of the Lord. For I am vndoubtly perſwaded (next after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, and the true profeſſion of the Goſpell) <hi>this day, this day</hi> I ſay, is now, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall bee, the moſt memorable and happy <hi>Day,</hi> that in this Land was euer commended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to poſteritie theſe 1000. yeares. Indeed, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of France, hath title of renowne, but wee know well the poſſeſſion thereof was gotten by bloud, kept with charge and loſt with diſhonour. But by his Maieſties lawfull ſucceſſion vnto the crowne, that which the great and deepe Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of England, forecaſt many hundred yeares to compaſſe; that which by dint of ſword, and much effuſion of bloud hath often beene attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; that which all the victorious Kings of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land often deſired, but neuer fully effected; that which the example of other Chriſtian Kings, and the wiſeſt nations teach vs; that which the very idencity of place, language, condition, nature, ſoyle, affinitie, and all in themſelues doe offer; the Lord God, who is wonderfull in counſell, and excellent in workes, that hath he ſweetly brought about: without preſent alliance in mariage, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tumult in warre, without wronge to any
<pb facs="tcp:755:19"/>ſtate whatſoeuer, <hi>Iſraell and Iuda, Scotland and England,</hi> are both one, the ſecret and wiſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God hath ſo ſetled it, O let the conſent and mutuall loue of both nations peaceably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it, and God in his mercie and goodneſſe ſeale it faſt for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iriſh expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. ceaſed.</note>Since his happy entrance into this kingdome, how well is the whole Common wealth eaſed and disburdened of the continuall and troubleſome <hi>charge</hi> of our Iriſh expeditions:</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Spaniſh broilcs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.</note>How Chriſtianlie are appeaſed, the vnchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and bloudy ſpoyles, robberies, and murders daily committed betweene Spaine and vs.</p>
               <p>Moſt Godly and amiable, is the confederate league concluded with our bordering neighbors round about vs.<note place="margin">Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate derate League. moſt chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> To ſubdue Nations, and enlarge Kingdomes, by conqueſt and bloudſhed to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and tirannous Princes, it ſeemes great glory and felicitie, but by good and Chriſtian Kings warre is neuer ſought, but enforced by neceſſitie. <hi>Faelicitas maior eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Malis fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas. Aug. lib. 4. Aug. de ciuit. Dei li. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>vicinum bonum habere concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, quam vicinum malum ſubiugare bellantem.</hi> It is greater honour and felicitie, to retaine the loue of a good neighbour concording in peace, then to continue the ſecret hatred of an ill neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſeduced by war.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iſocrates. ad Nicole</note>The wiſe Orator ſaith. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Faithfull and wiſe counſellers are the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:755:19"/>profitable and worthy treaſure,<note place="margin">Faithful Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</note> which any prince enioyeth. And is not the Common Wealth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, with as noble, faithfull and wiſe <hi>Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> of ſtate, as learned, ſtoute,<note place="margin">Learned &amp; vncorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> vncorrupted <hi>Iudges</hi> and worthy <hi>Lawyers,</hi> as reuerend <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſhining in their liues and learning, as euer age af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded:<note place="margin">Reuerend Biſhops.</note> all theſe (through the milde and wiſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of a gratious King) retaining their former dignities,<note place="margin">Goſpell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed.</note> and faithfully performing their duties both to God and to their King.</p>
               <p>Is not the <hi>truth of the Goſpell,</hi> moſt peaceably, eſtabliſhed and carefully profeſſed, with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend and conſtant ioy in hearing the word, and frequenting of prayer, as giueth example to all the proteſtant Princes of Chriſtendome? To ſee the populous Court of a mightie King, as peaceable, well giuen and religious, as the well ordered familie of a priuate mans houſe, what chriſtian heart will not ioy to heare it, and who can but magnifie the God of heauen to know it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mariage honored.</note>The ſacred bands of holy mariage, are they not tenderly kept; highly eſteemed, and haue they not beene ſolemnly graced in Court, to the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of all the Land?</p>
               <p>Euery great Cittie and incorporation, and euery part of the Land, is it not repleniſhed with Godly and <hi>learned Preachers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Learned and Godly teachers.</note> trained vp in the vniuerſities, able in ſome good meaſure to teach,
<pb facs="tcp:755:20"/>rebuke and exhort with good diſcreation and iudgement? What ſo is wanting and defectiue herein,<note place="margin">Confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as Hampto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> ſuch hath beene his Maieſties Princely zeale that hee hath referred the care thereof to ſpeciall Committies, that with all couenient ſpeede, <hi>Wales, Ireland</hi> and the <hi>Northren borders,</hi> might be ſupplyed and planted with learned and religious Teachers?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry Iacob</hi> in his ſeditious Epiſtle dedicated to the King,<note place="margin">H. Iocob.</note> is not aſhamed to affirme that the <hi>preſent Eccleſiaſticall orders are more friendly to Papiſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. Godly and approued. T. C.</note> 
                  <hi>Libertines and Atheiſts, then to the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Goſpell:</hi> an other alſo of the ſame rancke, ſets it downe, that wee may better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our ſelues in orders and ceremonies <hi>to the Turke, then to the Papiſts.</hi> What a ſtrange and dangerous poſition is this? O where is diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and pietie, where is Chriſtian loue, and holy moderation? Seeing the doctrine is ſound and good in the chiefe and maine points of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, why ſhould any man ſpeake ſo vnaduiſedly, in matters of leſſe importance? Alas wee alſo are bound to pray for you, to ſhew you the right way, and woe be vnto vs, if (as men pleaſers) we ſhall ſpeake againſt our owne knowledge, or that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould bee conſtraind, to ſubſcribe to that which is not conſonant with the truth. Heare therefore and as a wiſe and vnderſtanding peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at length bee ſatisfied. For vndoubtedly the
<pb facs="tcp:755:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>ceremonies of the Church, and eſpecially the vſe of the <hi>Corſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The vſe of the Croſſe approued by Origen. in Pſal. 38. Baſi. de ſpir. Sanct. cap. 37. Chriſ. tom. 2. hom. 55. in Mat. cap. 16. Hiero. li. 3. in Ezech. Aug. tract. 55. in Ioh. &amp; de vea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Dei. ſerm. 18. &amp; 53. Greg. Mag in li 3. in Iob. cap 33 Ambro. li. 2. cap. 7. &amp; other many.</note> ſo much excepted againſt this day, as the <hi>Standard of Chriſts honor,</hi> hath euer beene aduanced, and borne aloft in the eye of the Church, to the comfort of all good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, by the whole troupe of the bleſſed Fathers, the Charrets, and horſe-men of Iſraell. And ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally thoſe ceremonies vſed at this day in our Church, they are in themſelues indifferent, in number few, in vſe decent. They are peaceable in regard of conformitie, reuerend to breede de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notion in the people, and for continuance theſe 1500. yeares vncontrowlable: They are conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Scriptures, the expoſition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is confirmed by the iudgement of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant Fathers of the primatiue Church; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued directly by later interpreters, defended ſouldly by new writers, diſcuſſed by Kingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, agreed vpon by nationall conſent, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by higheſt authoritie, atteſted and made good by the approbation and iudgement of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neighbour Churches, as appeareth plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the confeſſions and ſeuerall articles of <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetia, Boheme, Ausburge, France, Flanders,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heluetia. 1. art Boh. 25.15.18. Auſ. art 4. Fra. art<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 32 Sand. 32. Sax. ar 20 Sweuel. cap. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> and <hi>Sweueland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a grounded principle, approued by the learned diuines in all ages. <hi>In iis rebus in quibus nihil ſtatuit certum ſcriptura diuina, nobis populi Det &amp; Chriſtiani principis iura tenen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia ſunt.</hi> In
<pb facs="tcp:755:21"/>thoſe things wherein the Scripture hath ſet downe no certaintie, the Lawes of the Chriſtian Prince, and of Gods people are with all obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to bee embraced.</p>
               <p>To proceede in this peace and proſperitie of the Church, concerning the <hi>Saboth:</hi> How gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally is it obſerued, how religiouſly ſanctified, euen in this great and buſie Citie, wherein the ſtreetes may often be ſeene in a manner deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and few ſtirring vpon the Saboth,<note place="margin">Saboth.</note> in the time of diuine prayer and preaching: The pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preaching frequented with infinite congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and mightie aſſemblies in this famous Citie; the diligent and daylie prayers, the deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and thankeſgiuing, the readineſſe and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, in heating the word of God both preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reade euen in this place where I ſtand, doth witneſſe what I ſay. O how faire and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a thing it is, for a Chriſtian King to heare and know, all the inhabitants of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to bee aſſembled vpon the Saboth, to bee knit together as one man, praiſing, ſinging and reioyſing in God all their prayers well neere at an inſtant, as the flame of a thouſand moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, aſcending aloft and peircing the very heauens.</p>
               <p>And is it not as louely to behold, all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of theſe Kingdomes,<note place="margin">Induſtry of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> with obedience to Law, and loue to their Soueraigne, to go peaceably on
<pb facs="tcp:755:21"/>as birds in the ſpring, buſied euery one in their ſeuerall callings, and all the weeke long cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully following their vocation?</p>
               <p>Hath not the <hi>Lord crowned yeare after yeare with his bleſsing,</hi> the Land giuing ſuch encreaſe that notwithſtanding there bee at this preſent, in this Citie and Suburbs <hi>ſixe hundred thouſand liuing Soules,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plentie.</note> yet they all are well and plentifully fed, and all the people throughout the land wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing warme and wealthie, ſit peaceably vnder their vines, taking their pleaſure and recreation? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. It is a waies an aſſured and good ſigne of excellent gouernement, when the people of any kingdome doe grow more wealthie, and become more ciuill and religious.</p>
               <p>What excellent and Godly acts, ſtand in force, for the wiſe ordering and comfortable reliefe of the poore? What ſtraight and holy Canons or,<note place="margin">Good Lawes,</note> for the religious proceeding in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Eccleſiaſticall? What ſeueritie is openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, and what puniſhment daily executed vpon corrupt Officers &amp; powlers of the people</p>
               <p>Hath not <hi>Mercie</hi> triumphed ouer iuſtice,<note place="margin">Mercie.</note> and compaſſion to forgiue (the perfect note of true Chriſtianitie) ſhewed it ſelfe abundantly in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning ſundry offences, and ſparing the liues of dangerous and hatefull Traitors?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:755:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Feare admitteth no ſecuritie:<note place="margin">Democrit.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whom all men are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of, ſuch a man, ſtands in feare of all men. And therefore, like a wiſe and right Chriſtian Prince he doth not build his ſafety vpon ſtrength and power, but vpon the mercie of God, vpon <hi>Princely affabilitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Affability</note> with his Nobles, and vpon the loue and faithfulneſſe of his ſubiects. <hi>Doctor Hill</hi> and other Papiſts, <hi>Iacob</hi> and other ſectaries, they ſlanderouſly auouch, that their perſecutions are many, and their afflictons very grieuous: and ye behold all diſſention in religion,<note place="margin">Milde go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</note> hath beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies labored and is ſtill ſought, by all forber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and gentle meanes to be appeaſed: yea to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, all men in generall, the <hi>gouernement is ſweet and milde,</hi> and himſelfe in his priuate na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo louing and compaſſionate,<note place="margin">Ambro. de obitn. Theod.</note> that as <hi>Theido.</hi> hee ſeeketh to binde men vnto him, not by force, but by bountie &amp; religion. Troubleſome and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious ſpirits will neuer ceaſe to murmure and complaine,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciuit Dei lib. 1. cap 8.</note> but the point is: <hi>Non qualia, ſed qualis quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> patiatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since his bleſſed Raigne doe not our hearts ſecretly tell vs, that wee feele and daily taſt of ioyfull <hi>Peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Peace.</note> ſought by mightie Kings and embraced by forraine Nations, as in the daies of <hi>Solomon?</hi> Is not true <hi>Nobilitie,</hi> honorably reſpected? <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> and well doing cheerefully rewarded? <hi>Holy
<pb facs="tcp:755:22"/>men</hi> and diſcreet daily aduanced?<note place="margin">Vertue rewarded.</note> the <hi>reuenewes of the Church</hi> lately confirmed: and diuers <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations,</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> already laid, as in the glorious raigne of great <hi>Conſtantine?</hi> The Lord is God, the Lord is God, and who is ſuch a God as our God. O wretches, and vnthankefull men that we are, wee know not our owne good, we weigh not the ſweet mercies of a kinde and gratious God. For in theſe and many other reſpects, which are moſt apparant to the view of all men, I aſſure my ſelfe that his royall Maieſtie (whom the Lord protect with his mightie hand long to reigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs) is now, and ſhall bee for euer renowned amongſt the moſt famous Kings, that euer liued in the world: and that the Church, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth of England, ſo happely gouerned by his Highneſſe, is now at this day the moſt Apoſtolike and floriſhing Church, the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Court, the moſt peaceable and vpright ſtate, that is in all Chriſtendome: How bee it when Prince and People, when Nobilitie and Clergy, when all eſtates and degrees, doe thus Godly and peaceably go on, enioying ſuch bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed happines, ſuch quiet, and repoſed peace, would not the Sunne bee abaſhed, and the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of nature daunted, that Chriſtian men, and eſpecially ſuch as are deuoted vnto God in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and holy orders, ſome profeſſing great <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and auſteritie,</hi> others <hi>much pureneſſe and
<pb facs="tcp:755:23"/>great ſingularitie,</hi> both theſe ſhould neuer ceaſe to diſturbe and waken the churches peace? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is the Lord that giueth his beloued ſleepe, and this ſleepe, this proſperitie of the Church, and Common Wealth, it is a bleſſing ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto his people, therefore when hee vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth to giue reſt, no man ought to waken or ſtirre <hi>vntill ſhee pleaſe,</hi> and that is <hi>neuer</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>vntill</hi> it is plainely <hi>neuer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vntill.</note> 
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 8. <hi>The Rauen return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not vntill</hi> the waters were dryed vp, that is <hi>Neuer. Mat.</hi> 1.25. <hi>Ioſeph knew not the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin vntill</hi> ſhee had brought forth her firſt begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that is <hi>Neuer, neuer, neuer</hi> let any man wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the bleſſed Spouſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclution">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt for as much, as the perſon, from whom this Commiſſion is directed, is the <hi>Metropolitane and great ſhepherd of our ſoules, Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> the penner of the <hi>holy Ghoſt the heauenly Secretary: ſeing hee</hi> vouchſafeth to call the Church his <hi>Loue,</hi> the deepeſt of all the affections: her peace compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Sleepe,</hi> the ſweeteſt comfort in nature: ſeeing Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, moſt wiſe, louing, and fearefull, is not content to perſwade, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently to <hi>charge,</hi> and yet the attributes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb facs="tcp:755:23"/>moſt ſweet and kind, <hi>Daughters</hi> for Loue, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for peace: ſeeing the Charge it ſelfe is ſo ſtraitly giuen <hi>not one to ſtir,</hi> and in no caſe <hi>to Waken,</hi> the Date ſo plainely ſet downe, that is, muſt bee <hi>Neuer,</hi> according to the tenure of my text, in the perſon of Chriſt Ieſus, I adiure and ſolemnly charge: I charge by the holy <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> who in their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, were men of <hi>Peace,</hi> I charge by the <hi>holy Apoſtles,</hi> who haue commaunded vs to keepe the vnitie of the Spirit in the bond of <hi>Peace:</hi> I charge by the <hi>holy Angels,</hi> who at the birth of Chriſt did ſing <hi>Peace:</hi> I charge, by our <hi>Faith, Hope</hi> and <hi>Charitie,</hi> which are the fruites of <hi>Peace:</hi> I charge by that <hi>Obedience,</hi> due both to the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil Magiſtrate and ſpirituall gouernour, who are by all good meanes to preſerue and maintaine <hi>Peace:</hi> I charge, by the <hi>Dum Beaſtes</hi> of the field, who ſhall take reuenge vpon the diſturbers of <hi>Peace:</hi> Laſtly, I adiure and charge, by the <hi>Soules of the ignorant and ſimple people;</hi> the leaſt whereof a thouſand worlds are not able to redeeme, that no man deſpiſe the voyce of this great ſhepherd this double and three-fold Charge, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the flowriſhing and happy peace of our country, the proſperitie and peaceable reſt of the Church; the beeing, liuing, and well being of vs all.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer hath any true taſt of a religious
<pb facs="tcp:755:24"/>heart: whoſoeuer hath any care of his Soules Saluation: whoſoeuer hath any reſpect to the honour of his name, and regard of his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: whoſoeuer hath any dutifull affection to his Prince and country, let him pray rather that his tongue may cleaue to the roofe of his mouth, and his right arme wither from his body, then once to bee accounted amongſt the number of thoſe, who will bee ſeene to ſtirre in ſo well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned a ſtate, to waken ſo bleſſed reſt of the Spouſe, to diſcontent the religious heart of ſo gratious a King, and to blemiſh the glory of ſo renowned a Common Wealth.</p>
               <p>Ah Lord, what eſtate of Church or Common Wealth did euer in this world at thine vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and wiſedome could euer content all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours? wherein haue not the moſt Noble and Chriſtian Worthies of the world beene ſought, one way or other ſecretly to bee wronged? and who knoweth (touching theſe late and grieuous treaſons,) why the Lord hath ſuffered euill coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to bee vndertaken and with ſuch malice and bloud to bee purſued?</p>
               <p>Vndoubtedly, Firſt, it may bee thought to this ende, that all the people of this Land, and euery one heere preſent, might take heede how wee forget our louing God, in the dayes of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie,
<pb facs="tcp:755:24"/>that wee might learne, to <hi>ſtand faſt,</hi> vpon the Lord, as vpon mount Sion, to <hi>relie</hi> on his loue, as the centre of our life, in all dangers to <hi>ſtye</hi> vnto him, as a Bird doth vnto the ſhadie hill for ſafetie, that ſo both heart and tongue might acknowledge his gooodneſſe, and as a floud into the Sea, ſend thankſgiuing to ſo deare a God againe.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
                  <hi>permittit Deus quod nemo impunè committit,</hi> God ſuffereth euill and wicked men for a time, expecting their repentance and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their conuerſion, but, if they perſiſt, and become as <hi>Pharao</hi> was, hardened in their bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty crueltie, then the Lord, euen for his owne glory, doth ſuffer them to play vpon the hooke, and daunce in the ſnare, till at length it might bee knowen, to all Nations and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, round about, that when it comes to the very poynt, the Lord will rouſe himſelfe like a Gyant, turne all ſuch practiſes vpſide-downe; but will deliuer his choſen, execute iudgement vpon the wicked,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> and the <hi>vngodly ſhall bee trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the works of their owne hands.</hi> Therefore let neither Prince nor people, bee diſmayed, and caſt downe with traiterous and fearefull rumors, but let his ſacred Maieſtie, comfort his heart, raiſe vp his Spirit, and walke cheerefully vpon the inuincible hope, and aſſured experience of
<pb facs="tcp:755:25"/>the Lords fore paſſed loue, let him hold ſtill faſt by God, and aſſuredly, height and depth, edge and point, ſhall fall and flye before him, all his croſſes ſhall afford him ioy, his enemies aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and his account ſhall cheerefully bee caſt vp for another world.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, the Lord hath ſuffered, euill counſailae thus farre to preuaile, that euery priuate man who liues in peace and ſafetie, might conſider and weigh, what a grieuous burden it is, to ſway the Scepter of a Kingdome, how the Kings life is hunted after for our ſakes, for the happines which wee enioy, how <hi>Hee and his Nobles</hi> are in continuall danger, how (not for himſelfe) but for vs, for vs it is, that <hi>Hee and his Poſteritie</hi> is purſued with ſuch deadly hatred: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the Lord ſtands cloſe vnto him, hee hath faſtned the crowne vpon his head, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Scepter in his hand, mauger the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all his enemies, and the rage of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell himſelfe, hee will haue all the world to ſee, that hee hath ſet him vp, to bee the onely meanes both of eſtabliſhing our happineſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed, and alſo of diſcouering our danger eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: that ſo, when all the people of this Land, ſhall plainely ſee, how the Lord hath ſet his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light vpon him: how from the very cradle hee hath lapped him in the boſome of his loue, how
<pb facs="tcp:755:25"/>hee hath puld him out of the iawes of death, from <hi>Poiſen</hi> ready to bee taken, from <hi>Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> at an inſtant, from the <hi>Lake of Fire,</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to bee kindled: wee and all his Subiects, might bee moued, to loue him with a dutifull and entire affection, to pray for him, as for our owne Soules, to ioy in his proſperitie, as the life of our well doeing, to eſteeme him in our thoughts, and honour him in our hearts as a tender Father, beeloued of God, the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Religion, the giuer of peace, the ioy of his Subiects, the honour of all Chriſtian Princes, and that with ioy and thankſgiuing wee might ſing and ſhowt this day. <hi>God ſaue our King for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now therefore O Lord our GOD, who dwelleſt in the higheſt Heauens, infinite in goodneſſe, abundant in mercie, and glorious in prayſes, wee magnifie thy name, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in thy mercie, for that, ſtill wee doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye this happy day. Alas, of our ſelues, what is our King, and what are wee his Subiectes, that from time to time, thou ſhouldeſt ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly loue him, and ſo continually follow vs, with thy gratious and ſweete mercies? Wee know O Lord, <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Honour, Peace</hi> and <hi>proſperitie, Life</hi> and <hi>Deliuerance come onely from thee: Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Power, Glory, Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie</hi> and <hi>Prayſes they are thine:</hi> and what ſhall wee render vnto thee, our deareſt God? One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:755:26"/>this. Beefore Heauen and Earth, beefore thy holy Angels, beefore all thy Saints, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts, heere preſent in this publike congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee doe <hi>bow our hearts and the thoughts of our hearts vnto thee,</hi> wee acknowledge our owne vnworthineſſe, aſcribing all our happineſſe, and this our late deliuerance to thy fatherly protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on onely.</p>
               <p>We are heartely ſory, and doe ſecretly mourne in our ſoules, that for all thy kinde and vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able bleſſings, we cannot ſerue thee as we ought, nor loue thee as we would, but we entreat thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Maieſtie, ſtir vp in vs good deſires, encreaſe them more and more, crowne them with thine owne mercie, and wee will neuer ceaſe to ſing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting priaſes vnto thy name.</p>
               <p>Deare God and eternall Father, be pleaſed, be pleaſed to confirme this gooneſſe, and to eſtabliſh this thy couenant both with our King and vs thy people for euer. For thy mercy ſake, for thine own glory ſake, for thy Son Chriſt Ieſus ſake, forſake vs not, neither leaue vs, continue for euer our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, let vs and the remnant of our ſeed after vs bee ſealed vp, in thy mercifull promiſe, in thy gratious and euerlaſting loue, and that through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom, with the Father and holy Ghoſt, bee all honour, praiſe and thankeſgiuing both now and for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:755:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
